Here we go. We're going to do the We're
going to go back to the love room.
And
the good news I don't have any
announcements.
Again
in this point
in the ancient book
which is about
900 years ago.
He is just giving short advices.
And this first one is lama lama good
means uh
have fun with your teacher.
Have respect for your teacher, okay?
I like affection.
Respect is like this.
And then affection is like
And I like that kind of love, okay?
I like
we are friends and we're having good
time. We're having a good Dharma study
together.
So I like this kind of uh
I like this kind of respect. I don't
like this kind of respect.
You know.
I like
Here's
Here's Here's the
Here's a
donut. You're tall.
You know, something like that, okay?
Lama lama good so have fun with your
teacher. Have fun. If you're not having
fun, I think you're have a problem.
Okay. I think if you're too serious,
there's
some kind of problem, you know? If
you're happy, you're having fun, right?
So I think have fun with your teacher.
Have
fun with lojong.
Okay? Lojong is crazy.
Lojong is crazy, you know? Lojong means
uh
you know, there's 100 people
and there's only
refreshments and you're like
everybody else go first.
You know, and you
you let the other people have it first.
And you're like, "Ah, I didn't get any.
That's okay."
That's a lo jong. Okay, so have fun with
lo jong. I hate serious lo jong.
You can rub.
There's only one coffee left.
You You can take it.
You know, like that's I think so serious
lo jong is not lo jong, right?
He's like, "Rob, there's one more
coffee. Go get it. You know, have it.
Have it. You know, enjoy and have fun
with your lo jong. Okay, that's what he
said."
means
uh
Keep your
You know, when you study lo jong, when
you get bodhisattvas,
uh
These are the bodhisattvas.
Uh Dr. Shenma, first one.
You know,
stop uh criticizing other people and
praising yourself. That's the first one,
Dr. Shenma. Uh
so,
keep them happy, okay? Don't keep them
very serious, okay?
Have good time
with the lo jong. Have good time with
your bodhisattvas, okay? Know them.
Right?
You think I learned them in one day? I
didn't.
It was suffer for 6 months or something.
Okay? And work hard.
And then have fun. Have fun with the
bodhisattvas. Keep them. Have fun.
All right. Uh next one is a picture
of three doors.
You, Francisco.
Tres puerta. Tres puerta puerta.
Three doors. You guys got a picture for
me?
Mhm.
Anyway, okay, they're going to look for
them.
All right. Uh
Lola is in town on my shock bar. Deva
Lakhu. You guys know down jar, down jar.
These are the 18 leashes and fortunes
in the Lam Rim tradition. Here you have
the same word, telwa. Say telwa.
Uh and it says, don't do telwa.
Do not do telwa. Telwa means relax
uh with your good karma.
And he says, don't do it.
You know, uh if you still have a body
and if you still have a mouth
and if you still have a mind, for God's
sake, use it.
Do something with it, you know. Don't
leave your body
for a whole day without helping
somebody. Okay? So, your body wants to
be lazy.
And your mouth mouth wants to be lazy.
And your mind wants to watch Korean soap
opera on Netflix.
But fight, you know, push them. Telwa
Mashak means push them.
You know, they will get tired. What's
the best thing to do
What's the best time a thing to do when
you're tired of serving others?
Serve them more.
Okay? It's very refreshing.
Okay? It makes you much energy. Okay?
When you feel tired
Oh, this one this is means it this one
give me so much work, man.
What should I do? I said, get more.
Get more. The best way when you feel
tired
I'm telling you from grandpa, you know,
I'm much I'm double triple your age.
And I don't feel so tired, right? And
just when you feel tired, then work
harder. That's the solution for tired.
Okay. All right. So Lama Tsongkhapa
Gelugpa means uh push your body,
push your
speech, push your mind
to serve more people. Keep pushing.
Don't stop. Push harder.
People say, I I'm overworking in ACI.
What should I do?
Join YSI. Work for them.
Also,
that's my suggestion.
And it worked for me, you know. I have a
lot of energy and I enjoy my life and
and uh I was born before your
grandfather. Okay.
Uh look at Gewa Ni Cho Kor So Kyong Ba
Mingkyi. Mig Do Ngon Cha Ngon So Ma
Kyong Kyab Sung Kyong. Look at Gewa Do.
Do. Uh this is very beautiful advice,
okay?
Uh and by the way, these are again,
these are just short advices.
And then he's going to give you the big
one, which is the six perfections. So,
we're about to start the six
perfections. Tim, I think the next
program is Diamond Mountain in
in April,
right? Am I right? Yeah, we will
continue this book
at our retreat center in Arizona.
I'll tell you the ultimate story
of our retreat center.
Uh some lady from Shanghai
came to me at the retreat center.
And she's like, Geshe la, can I ask you
a question?
It wasn't Wang Xiao. It was somebody
else, okay?
And she said, can I ask you a question?
I said, yeah, I'll try.
She said, last night, did you see?
I'm like,
"See what?"
She said, "The whole sky
covered with stars. The whole sky.
Millions and millions of stars." We
chose a place where there's no city
nearby. We a retreat center.
According to the ancient knowledge,
you should build it in the empty place.
We found them It's one of the most empty
places in the world.
There's
no light pollution. It's completely
dark.
And the stars are unbelievable. And and
this
this Shangri-La man, I'm sorry,
Wangchuk, but it was
She said, "Here's my question." What?
"Last night the stars I never saw in my
life."
I said, "Yeah." She said,
"Are they coming back tomorrow?"
I'm like, "Yeah. They come back every
night." She said, "Wow." You know, and
then I feel wow, she never saw all the
stars. She think it's we invited them
for one night. And
uh you you will love the place. You will
love love the place. It's very
beautiful.
And to do retreat to get this teaching
during retreat is very very beautiful,
very very fun. And it's a beautiful
place, okay?
So, please come if you can come, okay?
Uh look at Gawa Ni Chak On.
And here's a beautiful advice. He says
uh
talking about physical good karma. You
know, good karma you can do with your
body.
He says, of course you can do
prostrations.
You know, my lama used to do like 100
prostrations, 200 prostrations.
I don't like it. It's too hard.
Uh then he says kora kora. It means uh
you can find a stupa
and you can walk around the stupa. These
are physical
good karma, right? But he says
that's not the only good karma for a
a real Lamrim person. No, don't look
tamed by sorrow. Sit up straight.
You know,
fix
help the chi in your body.
Okay? When you meditate, when you sit in
a Lamrim,
um sit up super straight, okay? Back is
straight.
Tummy is
is tight.
Shoulders are back,
you know, chin is mhm.
Not like
And uh he said, "You don't have to go to
a temple and walk around the temple.
Uh you don't have to prostrate to the
Buddha.
Just sit up straight
in your chair and help your prana.
Help your prana to move and it will help
your meditation. It will help your
health. It will help your your study.
Get in the habit of sitting up straight
all the time.
Okay? Not just when Geshe is there.
Okay? But especially at home, okay? Even
on the important chair.
Sit up straight, okay? And it's very
good for your prana. And it will help
your meditation. Just get in the habit.
Okay, I have the habit, right?
I'm always sitting up straight, okay?
Even I'm lazy with my exercise, but
sit up straight, okay?
That's the minimum.
And then, of course, using your body to
help other people, okay? But even
sitting up straight
so you can meditate better,
uh
that is good karma with your body cuz
you're thinking about your meditation,
you know, you're thinking about your
meditation. It you don't even doing it
directly for other people.
You are just trying to help your own
prana, so your mind is more clear. Okay,
get in the habit
to to sit up straight, and it will stay
like that after few years.
You will be like those military guys,
right Igor?
No.
Okay, subject anyway.
Okay,
someone turn making yoga.
Lojong che yun nyam dra dang nyen shye
dri su che pa dang.
So, do you lojong?
Uh serve other people.
Other people come first in lojong.
Other people come first, okay? Who gets
the coffee first? Other people. Who gets
the pastry first? Other people,
especially if Geshe la has the other
people.
Okay?
And always other people, always other
people come first, other people come
first. Lojong che yun
Then he has a very interesting uh
suggestion.
When we say other people come first, we
don't make a difference between your
enemies and your friends.
Okay, who gets the coffee before you?
Your friends and your enemies, equally.
Okay, people you don't like,
they get the coffee first.
People you don't like, they get the
donut
first.
Okay, and in the lojong, we rese che pa,
rese che pa means uh
have some kind of bias
that you you you draw a line between
your friends and your enemies. Lojong
doesn't know
discrimination,
drawing line. This is my friend, this is
my enemy.
Lojong doesn't
There's no drawing the line, okay? Treat
everybody
before you treat yourself.
And the everybody, no distinction.
Everybody.
Your enemies and your friends both. They
get to have the coffee first, okay?
Lays your chap and don't say don't say
don't remember Danny says something very
beautiful.
Don't discriminate
between humans and animals.
Don't discriminate between humans and
animals, okay? Animals have a right
to this world also.
Okay? They have an equal right to this
world. In in we I was thinking about
science.
If you ask people what's your religion,
you know, some people will say Muslims,
and Christian, Jewish, Buddhist, you
know? Here's the real religion is in
your pocket.
This is your religion, you know? You bow
down every day.
You know?
And uh
This represents science. Science made
this thing,
you know? And uh
If I say uh Buddhism says
I don't know, plastic water bottle can
give you cancer, you're like, I don't
know about that.
And then if I say Stephen Hawking says
plastic water bottle can give you
cancer, you're like, oh, I'm going to
stop drinking from plastic water bottle.
You You
respect the science more than Buddhism,
I think. We all do,
you know? If I'm flying home
uh from
I don't know, Osaka Airport, and you
say, "Hey, Rob's a good Buddhist. He
made the airplane."
I'll say, "You know what? I'll just take
United Airlines."
You know?
You believe in the scientist more than
the
uh you know, okay? So, that's
you know, you should
But we believe in science. It's more
I can say, are you Christian? Are you
Are you Muslim? What's your country's
religion?
But, really there's one religion in the
world, and this is it.
And And we are all society We all
believe scientist.
Oh, the rabbi say, uh
you know, use your
I don't know. Use a piece of wood for
your cell phone. And then Steve Jobs
say, use this one. Who you going to
believe?
Who are you going to prostrate to?
You know, I think it will be Apple
corporation or Huawei
or something like that. So, we we tend
to
uh believe in
in those first. And
And
science
principle
is that human is more important than
animal.
Okay?
Uh that's a big big principle. If we
have to kill 2,000 rats
to study the brain
of a human, if we need to
solve diabetes
we can take the organs out of pigs.
We can kill them. If we need a new
apartment building for humans
and there's lots of birds there, or they
can move.
You know, we are Science says, we are
number one.
And the animals are number two.
Uh even they are talking about the only
way to keep a human body
going
indefinitely is to
grow organs in pigs
and then kill them and put the organ in
the human.
And science That's a principle of
science, and they don't teach it to you
in the school.
But, it's a It's a principle of science
that the human is more important than
the animal.
If you have to kill 100 animals to
survive one human
then kill 100 animals. But, in the
larger
everybody who has a feelings
is equal in the Lojong.
Animals
are equal in the Lojong, okay? In the
Lojong
we have to respect animals. And if you
try, you can do it. Okay, if you think
about it, you can do it. You don't have
to eat animals. Maybe
those cavemen
they can't grow rice, they don't know
how to do it. Maybe they have to eat
animals, you know? But but we have
farms, we know how to plant food.
And we can we can eat we don't need to
eat animals. There's no reason to eat
animals. Why make them suffer?
They are oh
just uh they are small, they are stupid,
we can eat them. Okay, so eat your
babies also.
They are small and stupid also.
Then what's the logic? It's no logic,
okay? So you you can eat
you can I have all these friends from
Princeton University.
Then I told them I'm going to be
vegetarian. Even in the monastery, I
said I'm going to be vegetarian.
And they're all like, "Oh, you're going
to get sick.
Uh you're going to
if you don't get protein
uh you'll be sick, you know? You will be
weak."
You know, listen, all the people who
told me that are dead.
All of them.
I survived much longer
without meat, understand?
Uh so
in the Lojong
we're supposed to you don't divide
between your enemies and your friends.
And you also don't divide between the
animals and the humans, okay? And
there's another one here.
Samchen Samchen member
between
animal life and plant life.
You cannot make a big distinction, okay?
You are protecting life.
You are protecting You are protecting
the environment. You are protecting the
environment, okay? This It's important.
A monk is not allowed to cut a green
plant.
We are not allowed to cut a tree, for
example.
Why? For 2,000 years we're not allowed
to cut a tree. Why?
There's
It's their house. It's their apartment.
You're ruining the apartment of many
animals and birds, you know. Uh we can
cut a tree if we have to build a
monastery or something like that. We can
We can cut a tree. We're supposed to
plant some more tree.
Okay? So, it says here risu chepa,
uh if you guys want to learn
ri means uh drawing.
Rima means drawing. Like those sangha
paintings, those are rima.
They are painted. They are drawn. Ri
means to draw a line. Risu chepa means
don't draw a line between humans and
animal Don't draw a line between humans
you like and humans you don't like.
Don't draw a line between humans and
animals.
animals and plants. Respect the world.
Respect the environment. Take care of
it, okay? It's very interesting. Lojong
is the Lojong respects the whole
environment also, okay? Very beautiful.
Uh sem chen chö nyi me chepa jowa
And it's funny cuz he says, "Jong your
lojong."
Jong your lojong without risu chepa.
Don't Don't make these distinctions.
You're serving all life.
And And you can't say I will serve some
life and I won't serve other life.
That's
That's not lojong, okay?
All right, that um
they they you turn the cover.
No thing they join check out the good.
Uh take all those you you means uh
objects
uh animals, birds humans
trees
planet
and chap chap means
cover them with your love like a
blanket.
You know, cover the whole world with the
soft blanket of your love.
This is tasty, right?
Better than cinnamon roll. Almost.
The real stuff.
Yeah,
so take the blanket of your love
and cover the whole world with it. And
don't make
don't say I will do it for them, but I
won't do it for them. Cannot say that,
okay? Love joy to
check out the tiger. Check out the is
lived the
900 years ago and uh
he wrote down these instructions for the
first time. But they were oral
instructions for about 200 years before
that, okay?
All right.
Next picture you guys. What's the next
item?
I think they lost my item.
It's a dynamite stick, you guys. Number
21. Picture number 21.
Yeah, dynamite.
Okay.
Uh now he's going to talk about you
chapaching. Say you.
Chapaching.
Special karmic objects. Okay? Certain
people in your life are more powerful
like dynamite.
And some people are not so powerful,
okay? Certain people you're not supposed
to distinguish
between friends and enemies. Take care
of your friends. Don't take care of your
enemies. But,
there are people who are super powerful
in your life.
And you should
be careful around them. They're a
dynamite.
Okay, for karma, they are dynamite
karma. Okay, what's what's an example?
Number
one,
if it's difficult to love somebody, they
are special.
Okay?
All right, I'm sorry. The person who
pissed you off the most
is powerful karma for you.
And you have to be super careful. They
are dynamite for you. Okay, if there's
three people,
one you love them,
one you never met them,
one of them always piss you off, who's
the more powerful?
The one who pissed you off. Be careful
around the dynamite. Okay, like be more
careful with that person. Treat them
nice.
Treat them nice. They are more powerful.
Karmic object more powerful. Okay.
That's the first example.
Second
example, he says
"Your nyamba lama pama shavro."
The people you are around all the time
are powerful karmic object for you.
Okay? And you take them for granted.
Your wife, your husband, your kids.
Okay? You The people you work with.
Uh we tend to
take them for granted and we say things
that we will never say to an other
people.
And we do things we will never do to
other people. And we think they will
still love me.
Usually they do.
Okay, sometimes they kick you out. Okay,
so uh he says people that you are around
all the time. And he gives a list. You
remember means close family, brothers,
sisters,
mother, father, kids.
Okay? They are dynamite.
Okay? Then he says lama,
your teacher. Okay?
And lama doesn't have to be a monk in a
robe. Lama children are very good lamas.
They I Nick became a good student after
he got the real lama.
Her name is Lama D.
Okay?
Uh so lama.
Hama, that was my examination, my Shanti
Deva examination. Papa, mama.
Okay?
And then shakra shakra means your close
friends and colleagues at work.
People you work with, people who are
people you hang out with. Chakra means
people you hang out with. Okay?
Sha means literally uh
amongst.
Room is called a sha. Rok means your
friend. Sha shakra means the people you
work with, the people you hang out with,
like that. Okay?
They are all more powerful karmic
objects
because you're around them a lot. Okay?
That's dynamite.
Dynamite can
We're making They're making a new road
in Arizona and it's cool
cuz there's a mountain there.
And we see the progress every every week
or something. And they take dynamite and
they blow up the mountain and it's kind
of sexy,
you know? And they are making a new road
that everybody needs. It's a good road.
And
but also uh
dynamite can be powerful for good things
and dynamite can kill many people. So,
you know, okay? Uh
Fabio Sudoku and thing Jong Bong Kong.
Thing means that deep down inside of
you. Thing.
Okay? In your thing. It also means the
bottom of the ocean.
So, it means
down inside of your heart, in the bottom
of your heart.
Be careful around this dynamite.
Okay? Be be super careful. The problem
is we get used to these people. Oh,
Anna's around every day.
You know, why should I be nice to her?
She's just hanging out here all the
time.
You know, and we get I get used to my
wife, you get used to your kids.
And they are actually more powerful
karma because you're around them all the
time. So, be careful
with the people you're around all the
time. They are more powerful karma for
you.
They are dynamite for you, okay?
Cool?
All right?
All right.
They all say "Gesul tun kenzom zomma
topa gomban ne."
Uh
say zom.
Zom means all the stuff you need has
come together. In English,
we say "God, it all came together."
What?
We got the Lindsay to run the program,
we got all the regional directors, the
books are ready,
Rose is on board with
with the B case,
we got Tim talking about it at his other
program,
and
all that zom. Zom means everything we
need came together, okay? That's called
zom.
He says
keep your lo jong whether the tun kenzom
or not. Tun ken means stuff you need to
do a job.
The money to do this program,
okay? The time to do this program, the
place to do this program,
the airplane ticket to do this program,
okay? Those are called tunkin.
Uh
in YSI, and we're going to have a class
in January,
in YSI, there's a beautiful description
of the tunkin.
The things you need to bring together
zone
to do retreat. For deep yoga retreat, to
do deep yoga practice,
you have to zone,
you have to bring together all the
tunkins. Uh tunkin means food good food,
healthy food,
uh quiet place,
no bugs,
no bugs and no bugs.
Okay? I'm talking
the Hatha Yoga Pradipika, the book we
are studying in January
for the Yoga Studies Institute.
The first thing the guy says,
uh 500 years ago, Svatmarama,
he says, "Find a retreat place with no
bugs." And when I saw no bugs, I said,
"This guy knows what he's talking
about."
Cuz when you're trying to do a deep
retreat, the bugs drive you crazy, okay?
Uh so, he's I said,
"Then I'm going to read the rest of the
book."
Because he knows what he's talking
about, okay? That's called tunkin zone,
okay? Zone.
He says,
"Lojong is independent of tunkin zone."
Okay? You have time or not,
effort,
keep your lojong.
You hungry or not,
effort, keep your lojong. You sleep You
didn't sleep last night,
keep your lojong, okay? It should be
independent
of things going on around you, okay? You
You're hungry or you're not hungry.
You're rested or you're not rested. Your
friends are there or your enemies are
there.
You should be independent, okay? Keep
your mojo. Keep your compassion. Keep
your care for other people.
It shouldn't be dependent on how you
feel.
Okay? Ignore how you feel. I don't care
if you're hungry. I don't care if you're
tired.
I don't care if you just served the Lama
Rinpoche for 25 hours. I don't care.
Keep your mojo. It should not affect
your mojo.
That's very difficult, you know? If I
don't get
a nice dinner, I get grumpy.
Okay.
But I'm not supposed to.
Okay. Gomba le.
And then he gives a uh
he gives a nice poetry. Okay, here's
some poetry.
Uh to da nyi me choe de che be so
khen nyen toed pa tsal che ta me wa.
This is poetry.
Uh Buddhist poetry, okay?
To dang means uh your belly is full.
You got lots of
ponchiks
in your belly or youtiao.
Why does
the word in every language
for donut?
Uh to dang
your belly's full. Nyima tsal means
the weather is perfect.
The sun is out. It's not too hot, not
too cold, okay? It's like yesterday in
Kyoto.
You know, beautiful weather, you know?
Uh trees are beautiful. Everyone's
relaxed, you know?
Belly full
good weather. Belly full, perfect
weather.
Che be soe means
in those conditions, you can pretend to
be a Dharma practitioner.
Soe means soe be nyen means uh
reflection.
This che is without the apostrophe. So
che ba here means Dharma practitioner.
You know, as long as your belly is full
and as long as the weather is really
good,
you're a nice person.
Like, you know what the next verse is
going to say.
All right?
Okay.
Uh Khenpo and Tulku Pema say,
"But when problems hit you, Tulku Pema
Tulku Pema means suddenly. Suddenly you
get a problem. Like you're
you're getting on the airplane, it's
business class.
Everything's good. They're already
cooking the dinner. You're like,
and then they say 12-hour delay.
It's like the
Excuse me, my wife doesn't says I
shouldn't curse during lung room, but
the hit the fan.
And you're like,
you know, they said 12-hour delay.
Forget the business class. Here you can
have $2
you know, food ticket. You're like,
"Thanks."
You know,
so when
when people hit the fan suddenly,
we lose our lung room. We tend to lose
our lung room. You know, everything's as
long as things are going smooth,
I'm a great lung room practitioner.
Then somebody say 12-hour delay on the
flight. What? You know, no more lung
room. You throw all your lung room in 2
minutes, right?
Okay. So, he says "Tamawa." Tamawa means
I'll give a $1,000 for Tamawa. $1,000.
Tamawa. Wait, raise your hand. I'm not
giving the money easy. Tamawa.
Tamawa. Come on.
If it's $1,000, I will take a guess at
least.
Tamawa. You sure?
Nice. $1,000.
Where's the money, honey?
Oh, you're going to pay him later.
Did you hire a driver to hit him with
the car?
He will pay him though. He He knows him
well. In English, there's an idiom for
you.
We're good for it. We're good for it
means we will pay.
Okay, we're good for it.
Okay.
Yeah, tamel means normal person, okay?
Normal person.
Here it's supposed to chipasu.
In the mind In the mind before
it says when the weather's good and your
belly's full, you look like a Dharma
practitioner.
Then somebody canceled the flight
or you know, the restaurant closed today
for remodeling.
And then suddenly you're in tamel.
Then you're just a normal selfish
person.
person, okay? Why I pay so much money
for normal selfish person?
Why I pay Why I pay him a thousand
dollars for such a small word?
In the In the diamond way, okay? In
normal Buddhism
like the one of the worst thing you can
do is to kill another person, okay? One
of the worst thing you can do
in normal Buddhism
is to kill another person, okay?
In higher Buddhism, diamond way
Vajrayana
more serious than killing another person
is to believe there are not at least
three Buddhas in this room right now.
That's worse than killing a person in
high high high Buddhism.
Okay, in high high Buddhism
you're supposed to believe
at least two or three Buddhas sprinkled
in this audience.
Then it's fun to guess who it is.
Then everybody's like, "Not me."
You know,
by the way, it's not me.
Okay. I mean, I'm working on it, but I'm
not there.
Okay, but in the high high Buddhism
uh
we're supposed to
practice as we practice someone
maybe one, maybe two
how many people here? 200 people
something.
Yeah, maybe 200 people here are Buddha.
I am not.
I'm really I'm not.
Uh
but I I sometimes
think
you let me to teach the Lamrim
cuz I'm the only one who's not.
Okay, and uh thank you for that.
Um but uh
you don't know. Yeah, you don't know,
okay?
Uh
Don't agree.
Okay, so
in in the high high high high teaching
the word for
the word for there's no Buddhas here
today is tamel. It's the same word.
That's the word. It's a very
bad word
in the high high teachings. It means
there's no Buddha at all in this room.
Everybody's normal.
Everybody is who they look like.
And inside they are not Buddha, okay?
That's called tamel.
And to believe that
about any audience
is worse than killing a person.
in Buddhism.
Very interesting. Really interesting.
Okay, you got to think about it.
Everybody asking grandpa to teach
Diamond Way.
Maybe I'm teaching it all the time.
You just didn't know.
All right. Today I taught you the real
one.
All right? Think about it. Okay? And if
you really want to have fun He said,
"Have fun with your mojo, right?"
Anytime you go anywhere,
like we're going to go to a nice
restaurant tonight. We're going to take
a break. Finally, grandpa gets a break.
Just going to eat.
And uh it's very fun
Buddhism
to look in the restaurant, who's Buddha?
You can play a game
with your friends. Go with your Lamrim
friends
to the
Tokyo
tea shop
restaurant
sushi restaurant
and and say
"There's one person in this room is a
Buddha." And then talk about it.
I think it's that guy over there. Nah.
He's too obvious. Normal.
You know, should be
I don't know. Should be You know, and
then have fun with it, okay? If you if
you want to
study Buddhism
uh do it in the restaurant. Do it in the
coffee shop.
And have fun. And say
By the way, I'll I'll tell you some fun
real fun.
Uh when you are alone, go to a coffee
shop.
And in your heart, silently
say
"Who's the Buddha in the room?"
And then watch.
Like she's doing it right now.
I saw it. I saw you.
Okay, watch the people. Somebody will go
like this, you know.
You know,
and have fun with it. Okay? Are they
Buddha or not? We don't know. Who knows?
They could be terrible person.
They could be Buddha.
But but checking
is a great great meditation. Everybody
say, "I want a deep meditation day."
Okay, go to the coffee shop.
Ask a question, "Who's a Buddha?" Now
look, she's doing this thing again.
Ah, I caught you.
Okay, so like that. Have fun Have fun
with it. Okay? Have fun with it. I
taught one student uh
what's her name? Mercedes. I taught her
to do that.
And she went to the mall and uh
I told her you look for Buddha, you
know.
And uh she went to the mall and she went
to the
like Takashimaya or some
expensive
clothing store
to look for the Buddha.
And one uh saleslady
in the expensive clothing, she's like
Then Mercedes like, "Huh? Huh?" And she
prostrates three times.
She prostrates three times on the floor.
Then the lady called a security guard.
Some crazy lady
Maybe security guard also Buddha.
I don't know, but it was beautiful. It
was really fun.
Okay, don't be scared.
A Buddha shouldn't be scared to make a
fool out of yourself.
Okay?
A
compassionate fool is better than a
non-compassionate
smart guy.
Understand?
Okay, better.
Then he says, "Look,
why we
practice
uh
this lojong
which is kekar. Kekar means it's a
difficult practice. It's a difficult
practice.
To treat your enemies and your friends
the same is not easy.
Uh
denchawa. Denchawa means difficult to do
and very powerful. Okay, difficult to do
and very powerful.
Do it for yourself and others,
but not just for this life, okay? So,
there's a very interesting definition of
Buddhism. You know, we were playing
with Tim's book.
That's not some stupid uh arguments.
It's a question. What is Buddhism and
what is not Buddhism, okay? That's a big
big
That's a
If you don't decide that, how can you
study?
You know, I'm studying Buddhism. What's
Buddhism? I don't know.
Okay. Uh
here it says,
uh
and it's a tradition in lojong.
Uh
If your if your lojong practice, if your
lamrim practice is limited to this life,
it's not Buddhism.
That's weird. That's powerful. That's
powerful. I'll say it again.
If your spiritual practice
is limited to this life,
before up to the time you die,
It's not Buddhism.
And I mean, all of us are trying to
meditate. We're all trying to practice.
We're trying to be good people.
We're trying to do the right thing.
But if your
picture of Buddhism ends with death,
it's not enough. It's not Buddhism.
Interesting, right? Okay. Your Your
goal,
your vision
has to be farther than that. Okay?
Beyond that.
And And a real Buddhist
has to be thinking in long longer terms
than death. Death is a small change.
And it has happened millions of times
for you.
And you have to be
Your practice has to be aimed at bigger
things.
Okay? Not just what this life. Okay?
This life, these friends, this world,
you know,
is nothing. You won't remember anything
from this world.
And it's a small small
small small
stop
on a big train ride.
You won't remember it in Later, you
won't remember anything
about this world. All the things that
are important to you,
you won't remember any of that. Okay?
So, your practice should be
bigger bigger thing.
Okay? Bigger than you and bigger than
this life. Okay? Cool.
Here's a little thing I made from the
poem He has a poem, though.
Uh
Next life rather than this one.
Dharma rather than the world.
And feeling towards others rather than
the book.
I think that one was for Geshe La.
You know,
and my wife will say things like that.
She'll say,
uh
You care more about the book you care
more about the Buddhist book than your
Buddhist students.
And then I'm like, "Mhm,
maybe you're right."
So,
not judging uh your book knowledge
about Buddhism, judging how you feel
towards other people. And these are
three famous
mental
uh advices, you know, focus on the next
life.
And don't focus so much on this life,
okay? This life going to be boom, over
like I
I had hair yesterday and I was surfing
and I remember the feeling of the board
when I stand up in Hawaii.
I remember that feeling. That's 50 years
ago, you know.
The time goes boom.
And you're like, "Oh my god." You know,
"Mhm."
Okay? You you won't even remember all
these things, okay? All the things that
are important to you now.
You you won't even remember them. When
you're my age, you won't remember them,
okay? All right. Next life rather than
this one.
Dharma rather than this world.
And feeling towards others rather than
study, study, study, okay?
All right. And that's difficult one for
me. I like study, study, study.
Uh
We we have some uh refugees from
Ukraine. We me and my wife invited to
two two refugees from Ukraine.
And uh we are taking care of them and uh
and she's like,
"We didn't ask them for dinner at our
house
for a few weeks."
And I'm like, "Honey, I have 200,000
students.
I cannot make dinner
for each one. It's not possible. I can't
do it. I just can't do it. I will have a
breakdown."
You know, she says, "We are having
dinner
for the Ukraine."
Okay, honey.
And we cooked the whole day for them
and uh
you know, she's like,
"The theory is a good,
but sometimes you have to do the real
thing
and invite the Ukrainian guys to
dinner." And we had a wonderful time. We
had two Russians, two Ukrainians.
We made the Christmas tree together.
Took it like 2 hours and
and we had a really nice dinner together
and
I decided afterwards that was Dharma.
That was a good Dharma practice, okay?
All right.
There's the instructions. There's that
one.
Uh we have a few more minutes. We have
10 more minutes.
And then I'll do question and answer.
So, maybe you start thinking about
question and answer. Uh it can be about
Lojong.
It can be about your personal life.
And it can be about
deep continuous teaching.
Okay.
Uh
Kolok Meja, Kolok.
Kolok means uh total opposite. In
English, we say total opposite. In
American English, we say total opposite.
Uh what's he doing?
What's that guy doing? I said, "I don't
know what he's doing, but it's the total
opposite of Dharma."
Okay. What's he doing? Kolok.
Uh it's the it's the total opposite of
Lojong.
Taking care of yourself and ignoring
other people is Kolok.
For Lojong, it's a completely opposite.
Okay, so Kolok, you can go like this.
Kolok.
No, you have to do the mudra. Kolok.
Yeah.
What's the impolite colloquial in
English?
Ass backwards.
Okay? The person's ass is in the front
and the other part is in the back.
Strange, right?
It means your practice is mixed up. You
take care of yourself before other
people. That's called Kolok. There's
three Koloks, okay? Sorry, six.
Six Koloks.
Let's do some of them. Let's see how
many we can finish, okay? There's six
different Koloks. By the way,
when you're doing a real meditation
retreat in April with us
at Diamond Mountain, just cuz you're
from Japan, there's airplane that come
to Arizona.
And you're very welcome to come and we
have a good time, okay? And it will
change your life.
My business success came from Diamond
Mountain.
Okay? I I made the largest diamond
jewelry company in the world
from nothing.
Um zero.
And I say it came from retreat. It came
from
It came from retreat, okay? So don't
say, "Oh, I'm very busy at my work. I
can't go for one week to Diamond
Mountain."
Okay, work the rest of your life for a
small salary.
Good luck.
Don't don't make a breakthrough.
You know, just keep working, you know,
like $5 and uh whatever.
Okay? If you really want
a breakthrough,
come and do retreat in April, okay?
If you want to have a breakthrough.
If you want to make the most
cool thing in the world,
you you need a retreat, okay? All right?
That New University, which we are having
MBA program day after tomorrow,
uh
she had that vision in a retreat. She
went to Diamond Mountain and did a
retreat. She and her partner, Connie.
And she got the Buddha was yelling in
her ear,
"Make a university."
And she is unusual cuz she listened.
And she made a university. One person
made like a $50 million university.
You know,
you can do cool stuff. Yeah.
In retreat, you can do cool stuff. Okay.
So, column meter, let's look at the six
backwards or opposite. Don't do the
opposite. Okay. Column meter. Number
one.
Chiky chawal la nim ru kachen mi suba
chi then chawal la kache suba suba
kolok. Say suba.
Kolok.
I put them in
Yeah, I will put them like that. Suba
kolok. What's suba mean?
Suba means patience. It's the fourth
Fourth? No.
Third.
The third of the six perfections. It
means the art of not getting upset.
Okay.
Third.
Effort. Fourth.
You pay me No.
Okay. So, suba means
don't get upset. When you're supposed to
get upset, don't get upset. Okay. That's
That's the third Bodhisattva's practice.
Very, very famous. When you're supposed
to get upset, you don't get upset.
That's called In In Sanskrit, it's
shama. Shh. Kushama. Kushama.
Shama. Sha came into English as Q U.
So, shama became quiet in English.
And it means stay chill, stay cool. Cool
comes from shama.
Uh Uh,
stay cool. Don't get upset. Don't get
angry. When something bad happens,
uh, don't get angry. But,
the same word shamatha means
high tolerance for pain
and high tolerance
for exhaustion.
So, sometimes shamatha means special
ability
to work hard even when you're exhausted
or even when it hurts.
It's called also shamatha. Same super.
Super, okay? It means, uh,
difficult situation,
tired, exhausted,
it hurts,
lots of trouble, financial, everything.
Trouble, trouble, trouble, trouble.
Shamatha means,
"I don't care.
I'm going to keep my practice. I don't I
don't care if I feel tired. I don't care
if things aren't going well.
Uh, I don't care. Doesn't matter. That's
also called
patience. It's a kind of patience, okay?
I I don't give up. I don't freak out. I
I don't worry.
I don't get discouraged.
Shamatha.
Shamatha. Shamatha literally means, "In
my heart, I am quiet."
Okay? That's going to cost a lot more
money than you think.
That's cool.
That's going to take 2,000 more hours.
Hey, guess what? The place you
reserved in Kyoto for the program is
canceled.
That's cool.
Okay, that's shamatha, okay? Uh,
So, sometimes shamatha means the
capacity to work hard when you're
already tired, okay? And that's what it
means here.
Why does he mention that?
Chiky jalala,
we don't do it. Jik tengi jalala, we do
it. How many times somebody said to you,
you know, uh I had this happen. Um
uh
you should meditate every day. You
should get up at 6:00 and meditate every
day.
And you're like, can I just do 7:00? You
know, I mean, I could do 6:00. I I have
an alarm.
It works. I can do 6:00. But, I'm not
top shape at 6:00, you know? I I'm
I feel tired. I I don't perform very
well. But,
the meditation is very dull
at 6:00. Could I do 7:00 instead?
And if the llama is smart, they'll say,
"Yeah, 7:00 is a very good time."
Any way to get you to meditate, they
will agree.
Okay?
You say, I can meditate, but only on the
toilet. A good llama say, "Great. That's
the best place." You know?
Okay?
Uh
Now,
uh if you've been looking for a job for
6 months, and you're trying to get a job
that pays pretty good money,
and somebody says, "I can give you a
job." And you're like, "Good." And they
say, "Is 200,000 a year okay?" You're
like, "Uh it's okay."
And then they say, uh "Can you come at
6:00 a.m.?"
And you're like, "Yeah, sure.
No problem."
That's color.
Okay? That's kshema color.
Okay? When it's some worldly work,
and the and they say, the boss say, "Be
here at 6:00 a.m."
And you're like, "How much is the
starting?" They're like, "300." You're
like, "Yes, I'm there." And you don't
you don't even hesitate. You're like,
"Yeah, I'm there.
I'll be there at 5:30 if you want."
You know, it's fine with me. I love to
get up early.
You know? Then the llama says, "Please
meditate at 6:00 or 7:00." And you're
like, "I don't
know, you know, I'm feeling really tired
and weak." That's uh backwards
patience, you know, okay? Got it? Super
glue looks like super
glue. Now,
there's a deep
principle of teaching Buddhism.
When the audience is having fun
and when they are interested and they're
waiting for the next five glues, stop
the class.
It's like
uh Korean soap opera.
I said, you got to see this opera, okay?
What's it called? King Kissing the King
or
King's Affection.
Yeah. I don't know how many times the
show
end with
banked cut and you're like, "Wait,
they're almost ready to kiss, finally."
You know, then they like, "Come back
next week." You're like, "What?"
You know, so
to cut the llama in class
just at the right time.
It's very, very bad luck
to hear one glue
and you didn't hear the other five.
Understand?
It's a special bad karma.
Your car going to break every day for
the rest of your life.
Okay? Something like that. Understand?
So, don't forget to come back online
or in person at Diamond Mountain.
Anything's okay, okay? All right, thank
you. Uh
Q&A.
What are the announcements or Q&A or how
do you want to do it?
Let's
long?
You tell me when to shut up.
We'll do three questions.
Can I ask you a lot of questions?
Okay, you decide who's
First one is going to be from Paling
online.
Yeah.
God, I need glasses.
How can I best protect and support the
minds of people around me?
Meaning sometimes my spiritual brothers
and sisters seem to drop into lower
schools of thought
or tell me about their poor worldly
habits.
Is there a good way to gently nudge them
towards
the Dharma without annoying them, and
but still maintaining warmth and
lightheartedness?
I didn't catch the essence just before
knowing them.
Is there any way to
Well, how how would they can nudge them
towards the Dharma in a kind way without
annoying them?
annoying
annoying annoying, yes
not annoying, but
But, what did you say just before that?
Oh, that
to correct them?
The right that that she sees them
falling into lower lower schools of
thought or they have bad habits in their
life.
And how does she help them without
annoying them?
Yes.
Okay, good. All right, good.
Uh according to
the laws of karma, right?
And we have this uh
We have a DCI course about controlling
your anger. What is it? What level?
Nine?
She says six, nine, and 10.
10, I think. Yeah. How to stop your
anger, you know, and supposed to be
uh in bottom. Supposed to be
uh
you find the fourth step
you have to find another person who has
a problem with anger.
And then you're supposed to help them,
you know, and
the best way
to method up
is to go to your friend and say, "You
know what?
Stanley, you're the most angry person I
know.
You know."
"Let me help you
control your anger."
And then the karma
of helping Stanley control his anger
helps me control my anger.
So, there's a
very famous mistake
with anger management
to do the four steps
by announcing to the other person, "You
are the most
pissed off person I ever know.
You know, you're always getting angry,
you know.
Uh
and they teach us in in the monastery
when you study Lojong
when you study four steps
it's much wiser
to pick the most angry person you know.
And by the way,
the most angry person you know
has no idea they are the most angry
person.
That's accepted. It's always like that,
you know.
Okay. So, go to the person who's most
angry that you know.
And and you do it this way, okay? "Hey,
Joy, you know, I got a problem."
And they're like, "What's your problem,
And I say, "I got this problem. I get
angry all the time, you know. I don't
know. I just have this thing inside of
me. I I get angry very easily, you
know."
"And
I was talking to my spiritual teacher
about it and
they said, 'Try to find someone who can
support you.'
And help you to So, I
I was wondering, could we meet in a
coffee shop once a week
and we can I can talk about my anger
problem and could you help me?
You know, like that. Um and that's a
better way. So, I would say uh
You want to hear another another
approach?
I gave a long teaching at Diamond
Mountain
about uh
if you're an irritating person
that karma
means that all the people around you
will become irritating.
You know, and uh
So, I taught it for like 2 days or
something.
And people come and go. They are
traveling from other countries and
somebody came
new person came
and uh
and and they they're very irritating
person. And uh everybody within 24 hours
everyone doesn't like this person and
we're all like so tired of this person,
you know? And then
then she yelled out
uh in English we we have an expression,
I'm surrounded by idiots.
You know, and all these
lamrim experts are like
because if you're a very irritating
person
the sign is that all the people around
you will become irritating. So, if you
are surrounded by irritating people
probably you have to work on yourself.
Uh and if you work on yourself
the people around you will change. And
and I can say honestly
you know, I have normal problems uh like
everybody, I have problems. I have
irritating people in my life and
and I try really hard
to remember that it's coming me, okay?
So, I'm just say
uh
it works, okay? It really works.
And you have all these uh how do you
call that?
It's not epiphany, but uh me-
meta- metamorphosis.
The person will change completely
in 1 week
or something. Someone's really
irritating me
and so and someone's really acting dumb
and and I will go home and I'll be upset
and tired and I got this person's really
I'm getting so tired of this person. And
then I will remember this thing called
Buddhism
and I'll say, "Wait.
Geshe la, they're coming from you, you
know? Maybe if you try to
stop that bad habit yourself,
maybe they will change." So,
I even did it this week. Here, I did it.
Someone was really irritating me.
And I went back to my hotel room and I'm
like,
And then my Buddhism kicked in.
Unfortunately, if you come to Lam Rim a
lot,
you develop a little guy in your head.
He says, "Don't forget.
It's coming from you. Don't forget. It's
coming from you." You know, I'm like,
"Ah, shut up." You know,
and uh
So, I tried not to act like that person.
And they changed com- completely, 100%
in 2 days or something. So, it's
So, if I'm have this problem that this
person has,
if I see my fellow Dharma students are
not being very nice,
maybe
there's a joke in English also. Maybe
you could change your seats.
Yeah. And and it's interesting cuz the
the Buddhist way
to change an irritating person
is to fix yourself. And there's no
tension.
There's no
difficulty. There's no bad feeling.
It's all silent.
It's all inside your own mind.
You know, you say, "I'm I'm seeing all
these irritating people. I must be
irritating. I must be doing something."
Then be a detective.
Be a detective, you know. "What am I
doing to irritate people?"
You can ask your friends. They will tell
you, "Everything you do is irritating."
Are you kidding me? You know, okay.
So,
fix it from the inside.
And they will change and and they will
change
completely. They will become your best
friend or something and it's it's very
cool. Okay? Look inside. Change inside.
Then the outside will change, okay?
Boom.